Now, we're oriented in the console. We can move around, and we can see where we are.
Let's actually start doing some work. File manipulation is important.
Just like on a desktop, we often want to add or delete files or directories.
We also want to view or edit the contents of a file or even copy or move it around the file system.
Let's learn how to do that.
So, we've seen how to move around and list files in our directory
for instance typing ls in our home directory shows us that there is a directory
and a file called hello.txt.
But that's not really helping us any. We're not getting any work done.
We're just traveling around and exploring.
Let's actually start looking at files and how we can manipulate them.
So, one thing we commonly want to do is see what's inside of that hello.txt file.
Now, there is a couple of different ways to do this.
One of these is a program called less.
Now, less is an interesting name for a program that will show you what's inside of a file
and that's because it's actually patterned after a different program called more.
Again, more is one of those programs that came with Unix.
Now, a lot of other operating systems can't just steal that program
so instead they create their own versions.
Sometimes, they have quirky names that somehow mimic the previous command that it's imitating.
So, in order to view the context of hello.txt, we are using the program called less.
Now, less takes out its argument the file that you want to view.
In our case, the file is hello.txt and you'll notice I use the tab completion
that Bash provided to me to fill in hello.txt.
And I just type a couple of letters and hit tab
and it knew exactly what I was talking about.
And I notice again this is what we called the relative path.
Because I am in our home directory and hello.txt is in it
I could just type in hello.txt.
I can also path the full path like /home/treehouse/hello.txt
but that's a lot of work especially since it's right here
but an absolute path will work just like it work in CD.
But we can also use any sort of relative way to get to our file.
Type in less and the file that I want to view and hit enter.
And I noticed something interesting here has happened.
Our prompt went away so did our history.
This is actually the program less, and it's taking up our entire console.
Some programs just print some output after our command and then show us a prompt
but some are interactive and take up our entire screen.
Less is one of those programs.
So, what we're seeing is the context of our hello.txt file
And I noticed there is a cursor at the bottom of the screen.
Now, this is not a normal command line, and this is actually how we interact with less.
So, we see there's a couple of paragraphs
and I've actually made this file longer than it needs to be
by splitting up one of the paragraphs to one word per line
so there's actually some more text that we can't see.
So, less is nice because it allows us to scroll through our text using our keyboard interactively.
If I hit the down arrow, you'll see that I can move up and down through the file.
Now, the cursor has changed a little bit
and that's because there are some commands we can use to move around.
Now, I'm not going to go over how to use less because there is a lot of cool things in less
as far as finding specific patterns within the file if you want to jump somewhere
but if we use our arrow keys it will scroll less one line at a time.
And another nice thing is if we use a spacebar it will scroll us one page at a time.
And for very long files that's nice.
Now, we can see at the bottom it has the end in parenthesis.
That's actually less telling us that's the end of the file.
The end of the file is after now here is the last line of the file.
That's the actual end of the file, but at the bottom is our prompt.
But we can still use our arrow keys to move around, but how do we get out of here.
Well, in less we use the q command
which means by simply typing q, it's going to quit out of the less command.
Awesome. Now, you remember I told you that less is modeled after more.
In fact it is, and one of the interesting things is sometimes when these programs
intend to replace or mimic a more historical program from Unix
that it definitely include like more
they'll actually assign the old name to the new program
so we can in fact type more hello.txt.
And it's more or less the same. You'll notice that it's a little bit different.
It's actually the same program running, but it's running in a way
to more closely emulate the older more program even though it's less handling it.
You'll notice I hit space, and it took us to the end
and it actually quit as soon as we got to the end.
So, that's a little bit how the more and less differentiate.
I would recommend using less over more because less is more
but less generally has some nicer features, although either of them will work.
So, now we've seen how to view the file in less or more, and this is something we called a pager.
We called it a pager because it showed us one page at a time.
But there are other ways we can see what's in that file.
One of those ways is to use a program called cat.
I'm going to use the clear commands to get our prompt to the top of the screen here
and cat will really just sort of concatenate all files together.
That's actually why it's called cat but it has this nice sort of side effect
is if we type cat and hello.txt
it just spits out the context of the file under the prompt like a normal program.
Now, what cat did differently from less is that it just printed out the entire text onto
our command line like some other files.
So if I scroll back up, you can see that it just printed it out
and we're back to another prompt.
Now, what cat is actually really useful for is concatenating different files together.
So, you can actually pass in multiple.
So for instance if we were to take a look at the document here about how to go home.txt
you can see the text here starts here and goes here so this is a different file
and what cat is really for is a way to actually print out one file after the other
which is useful in some ways that you may not think immediately
but later on cat can be useful for concatenating different files together.
So if we pass two different files like hello.txt and our documents how to go home.txt
by simply separating them by a space
There are two different arguments now.
And now if we scroll up, you can see that both files are printed one after the other.
So here's where it starts
and we scroll down and we can see the rest of the file.
So these are two different ways we can view a file.