And let's learn a little bit on how to move files and copy files.
Now if we take a look at ls here, we can see our file called hello.txt.
Now if I wanted to change this to be called hi.text
that would be something we normally call renaming.
But we can think of it another way instead of renaming hello.txt to something like hi.txt,
we can think of it as moving the file from one location to another.
Currently, it's in hello.txt, we want to move that file to hi.txt
and that's where the move command comes in handy.
Move is shortened to mv and it takes 2 arguments.
It takes from where we want to move something to where we want to move it.
So in our case we'll type in hello.txt and I can use tab completion for that
but our second argument that we need to move it to a place.
I can't use our text completion because we're moving it to a place that does not exist.
So I want to move it to hi.txt.
So I'm saying move hello.txt to hi.txt which is equivalent to renaming it.
And so if I hit enter and now we type in ls, we'll know see is hi.txt.
And if I type in less hi.txt, we'll see it's the exact same file and I just hit Q to exit ls again.
Now that's a simple case if we move a file within a directory
it's really just sort of renaming but we can actually move that one directory to another.
So for instance, if we want to move hi.txt into our documents directory,
well I can do this into documents.
Now since documents is a directory, I can just pass that as my second argument
and what it's going to do is it's going to move the hi.txt from my current directory
into the documents directory but with the same filename.
So if I execute this and now I type ls, we are going to see we only have our documents directory,
but if I do ls and passing documents as the directory that I want to list.
Again, I'm not moving into documents, I am just listing it from where I currently am.
Now we see the documents directory have hi.txt and how to go home.txt.
And I can move it back by doing the opposite.
So if I move documents, I can tab complete hi.txt again tab completing to our current directory
which I could do like that with a tilde or we saw how .. represents the directory above us
but there's another special directory called . which is our current directory.
So by simply typing . what I'm saying is I want to move
the document/hi.txt from its current location into my current directory
and . represents my current directory which in our case right now is our home directory.
So by doing that, I move it back into our current directory and we can see hi.txt is back.
Now remember before I use hi.txt and move it into documents without getting it a full filename
but if I gave it document/hello.txt, it would not only move the file into the documents directory
but also rename it to hello.txt within that directory.
So I type ls, we can see it's no longer in our current directory
and if I type in ls documents we can see it now exists in our documents directory as hello.txt.
So we've not only moved it from one location to another but we've also renamed it.
So that's how move can be a very powerful tool and then clear once again
and move will not only work for files but also directories as well.
So if I type in move documents and I want to rename it to docs, I can just do that.
And now if I type in ls, we can see that folder is now called docs
and we move it back to documents so by just typing in move docs to documents,
I can rename it back and again I can move document into another folder
and all the files and directories and site of that directory will be moved along with it.
Now we move our hello.txt back, so it's in our documents directory now.
It's in hello.txt and I want to move it back to our current directory.
So now were back to where we started and what if I want to make a copy of hello.txt
Well, I can use the copy command.
Let's clear out our console once again by typing clear.
And copy is shortened by cp for copy and copy works a lot like move
except it leaves the original one in place.
And if I wanted to copy hello.txt to hi.txt that's what I can do.
It's a lot like move but it leaves the original in place, so I hit it, type in ls.
We can see there's hello.txt so if I type in less hello.txt, we can see is that file.
And if I type in less hi.txt, you'll see it's the same file.
So I've just created a copy of it.
So if I wanted to copy a directory, however, it's a little bit different. Let's see what happens.
Now if I want to copy my documents directory into a docs directory,
I can try the same thing--documents to docs but I have a problem.
I can't just copy a directory--actually I have to pass this special option called -r.
This stands for recursive which means it will copy everything recursively.
By default, copy will only work on files but we need to do a directory and all the files within it
by typing cp -r, the source directory and the new directory you want to create from it
it'll recursively create all the files that exist in documents inside of a new folder call docs.
So by typing ls because there's docs and documents,
and if I type in ls docs, you can see it retains a copy how to go home.txt.
Again, that's a copy of the how to go home.txt that exists in documents.
There are two different files so it's recursively created a copy
of not only the directory but every file and every sub directory in that directory.
So that's why we need to do -r if we're copying directories from one place to another.
So if I want to remove the hi.txt, I would use the rn command which removes it.
So I'm going to clear it and will do an ls to see exactly what we have now.
And to remove the hi.txt which is a copy of our hello so that we don't really need it.
Type in rm for remove.
Now if I wanted to remove hi.txt, that's all I need to do.
Now you need to be very careful with the rm command
because it's not like in our desktop operating systems where we have a recycle bin
and we can go and undo it.
It's really just gone. There is not really an easy way to bring back from an rm.
So be very, very cautious when deleting files and especially when deleting directories.
Be careful not to hit enter too soon and maybe delete something you really needed.
So I've reviewed my command.
I'm sure I want to get rid of hi.txt and now I've done it.
There is no confirmation or anything so you can see how it could be kind of dangerous.
But if type in ls, we can see we're now down to hello.txt.
So what if I want to remove our docs. We'll let's try it. Let's clear out.
Let's type in ls to see what's going on. We have docs and documents.
I want to get rid of docs because it's a copy that we don't need to do rm docs.
But we've got a problem. We cannot remove docs because it is a directory.
Remember how in copy we couldn't copy it because of the directory,
the same thing works for rm.
Again, removing a directory could be way, way more dangerous than just removing a single file
because it's not only going to remove the directory but everything within it.
So again we need to signify that we are okay with recursively removing everything
not only in the docs directory but any directories inside of a docs directory.
So much like we did for copy, we need to pass through the -r flag.
So now we can remove the docs directory. Type in os and it's gone.
So what if we want to make a directory.
We have our documents directory and let's say we want to create a pictures directory.
We'll be using this command called make directory and that shortened to mkdir..
The mk we could think of as make and dir stands for directory mkdir
and we'll just give it the path that we want to do.
In our case, we'll say mkdir pictures.
Now we type ls. We can see there's now a new folder called pictures.
We can see that pictures is empty but we could place files in it.
Now say I want to create a directory inside of our documents directory
and maybe even a directory inside of that.
So let's say I want to have documents/notes/console.
I want to have that level of directory.
Now you might think, we could that by typing mkdir documents/notes/console.
So I want to create notes on my console within my documents.
Now the reason this won't work is because even though documents exists,
the notes directory inside of it does not exist so we can't create the console directory inside of that.
Now, there's two different things we can do.
We could mkdir documents/notes
and then mkdir documents/notes/console and that'll work.
But I'm going to show you another neat tip
for creating nested directories when you need them like that.
So now we have them, I'm going to ahead and remove
the notes directory by doing rm -r documents/notes.
Now if we take a look at documents, we're back to our beginning state.
If we mkdir -p, the -p option will allows us to create any level deep documents.
So we can see, say you wanted to create inside of the documents directory
which does exist--it happens to exist.
We're going to create notes directory and inside of that, we'll say console
and even inside of that we can say we can say part 1.
And it's going to go ahead and created all those levels deep.
So if we take a look at ls, we can see we have a documents directory.
We can go into documents--the ls, we can see there's now a notes directory.
We can go into that by typing notes. We ls that.
We can see we have a console directory.
We can go into that and if we can just continue tabbing through
we can see that there's even a part 1 directory.
So we see our prompt has gotten pretty long, let me clear it out.
And if we type in pwd, we can see our current location now is in our
home/treehouse/documents/notes/console/part1.
If you want to get home, let's use the .. to get home.
So we can do cd .. which would place us in the console directory/..
which would now place us in the notes directory/..
which would now place us in the documents directory /..
which would place us in the home directory.
Each.. takes us one level up.
And so now, if I calculate that right, we should end up in our home directory.
Bam! We did.
So there you are. You can now move around the computer freely.
You can add and edit and delete files in directories.
You now know enough console to be dangerous.
Next, we'll learn a little bit more about how the operation system works.