[Deep Dive: Console: Processes: What is Process with Jim Hoskins]
Processes are a core component of the POSIX operating systems.
Much like files and directories,
processes are what make it possible to run the operating system.
A process is simply an instance of a program.
For instance Nano, the simple text editor we saw earlier is a program.
It's essentially a file on disk that describes what a text editor should do.
When we call nano from the command line we are executing the program,
which creates a new process, which is the running instance of nano.
We could open nano at the same time in different console tabs or windows
and it would work just fine because even though they're the same program
they are distinct processes.
Like files, processes have information attached to them like a unique i.d,
who owns the process, when and where it started,
and how many resources like CPU and ram the process is consuming.
Let's take a look at the running processes on our computer.
From the console there are a couple of different tools we can use
to explore what processes are running on our machine.
One of the most useful ones is called top.
Top is like the task manager in windows or the activity monitor in OS 10.
You can run it by simply typing top and executing the top program.
This is program that will take up our entire screen and it will give us
up to date information on the processes that are running
and the resources that are being consumed on our machine.
This is particularly useful if you want to know if a process is taking up
a large amount of memory or CPU on your machine
in order to manage your resources.
At the top we can see some basic information
like how many tasks are running, how busy the CPU or CPUs are,
the memory that's being used, as well as some information about the swap
which is related to how much memory is being used.
Then we see this table.
As you can see it's updating every couple of seconds
based on it's current sort.
Each row represents a process.
The first column represents the process i.d.
As you can see right now, they start from 1 and go on up.
Every process on our system is actually spawned from another process.
Process number 1 the init is actually the first thing that runs
on our machine.
Init is responsible for actually bringing our entire system up
and everything works off of that.
Right now most of what we see are system based processes.
These are things we don't generally need to worry about.
It's generally not a good idea to try to stop these processes
but it's good to know what's going on.
As you begin running programs on your computer
you'll probably see those programs show up, as they consume CPU or memory.
Right now since we're not running very much,
all we can see is our system processes.
You'll notice that every once in awhile PID 902 which is our top process,
comes to the top.
That's because it's running and every once in awhile it does use a little extra CPU
and it appears at the top of our list.
This is an interactive program and you can find out more about how to sort on it
by hitting the question mark key, and this brings up the help.
The particular help that's available may change from system to system,
however one interesting thing to look at is how to sort,
in this case it's using capital F or capital O.
So let's go back by hitting another key, and if we type in capital F
we can select what we want to sort on.
Here it's giving us an interactive list.
The star indicates that we are currently sorting on CPU but if we want to sort on memory,
right now that's under the key n, so by typing n and then typing another key like enter
to go back, we are now sorting on memory as you can see.
We can go back and change this to whatever we want.
For instance the Pid,
and now it's sorting the Pid.
This is a nice program to know exactly what's going on on your computer,
particularly what's using the largest amount of resources if you are interested.
To leave this program all you need to do is hit the letter Q, and we're back.
Another tool we can use when we want to find out about the processes on our system,
is a tool called Ps.
I'm going to clear our screen so we can move the prompt to the top
by typing clear.
Ps is a program that will simply list out the processes.
In its simplest form if we just type ps, what we're going to see is just a couple of things
in a very small form.
These represent the processes that I'm running.
We talked about Bash briefly, and that's the program that's interpreting our keystrokes
and formatting the output on our screen.
It's the program we're interacting with, and we see that there's a process for Ps.
Which is interesting because Ps itself is a program that creates a process
and because that process is querying all the other processes
it always shows up in it's own search.
So you can see that when this ran we only had Bash running,
but we also had the Ps command running.
Now this usually isn't particularly interesting.
We want to know usually about more of the processes that are running on our computer,
rather than just the ones that are in our current session.
There are arguments we can pass to modify this, but the most common one is aux.
So Ps aux.
Now there is an interesting story in that these are technically options
which would normally be defined with a dash.
However based on different compatibility issues and historical reasons,
this is the most compatible way to define the options that we want.
Historically it means that we want to view all processes for the user x,
which means all users.
Now it's a bit confusing but just remember aux
will allow you to see all the processes on your machine.
So if I run that it's going to print it out.
Now notice this isn't an interactive program.
It simply returned all the data to me in the console.
So we could scroll up and see all of our commands right here.
Now the reason we usually want to use this tool is to find out:
A- what's running and B- the process i.d for a specific task.
In order to demonstrate this, I am going to run two programs at once.
Right now the easiest way for me to do that is with the Treehouse console
opening up a new tab.
This sends a brand new tab into our system and allows us to run two programs at once.
From this tab here I am going to simply run top, and I'm gonna leave this running.
So now if I were to do a Ps with aux to list all of the processes,
we can see that top shows up in our process list.
Now if we wanted to find out what process i.d it is,
for instance if we needed to maybe kill the process, this is how we would do it.
We could find it in this column here, and it has a process i.d of 1012.
You'll notice that this column here says pts/something
and these represent the actual terminals or windows into our system.
Because we have two different tabs here they represent two different
connections into the system.
So one of them is arbitrarily labeled number 2, and one of them 1.
Now if we're looking for something specific this can be a lot of stuff to parse through.
So we can use a special syntax in order to search the current processes.
We're going to learn a little bit more about the details of how this works in a little bit,
but right now let's just take a look at a simple example.
I still have top running in tab 2 and I want to find out the process i.d of it.
However I really don't care much about all the other stuff that's going on.
You can imagine in a system that's doing a lot more work,
this could be a much larger process list.
So if I'm looking for top what I can do is Ps, and we're going to use aux
so we can list everything.
Then we're gonna put a space and use the pipe character.
This usually involves holding shift and pressing the backslash key
which is usually the key above the enter key on your keyboard.
However it may be different based on your keyboard layout.
It should be this vertical bar right here.
We call this a pipe, and this allows us to combine programs together.
We're going to take the output of all of our process lists
and run it through a new toll called grep. G, r,e,p.???
Grep is a tool that allows us to take some input, search for a certain pattern,
and filter only the lines with that pattern on it.
In this case I only wanna see the pattern top.
So now, what we should see is two lines.
It took the entire list of processes and filtered it out to only the lines that have top in it.
It's also given us a color highlighting top itself.
Now you'll notice that it gave us two lines. Remember that the process that's
actually running it shows up in the process list itself.
So by running Ps through grep, that created another process that has the word top in it
because that's what we're searching for.
So to find the one that's top, we're going to ignore this grep line here
because this is the one that just completed, and we could find out that it's still on 1012.
If you are looking for a specific process i.d you can use PS aux,
a pipe character, grep, and the pattern you want to find.
This will particularly useful when you want to pause or kill a process.