[Deep Dive-Console-Processes: Pausing & Resuming Jobs with Jim Hoskins] ?[music]?
From a single console window, it seems like it is only possible to do one thing at once.
When we start an application--like the Nano Editor--
it consumes our entire window, and the command line isn't available for us to do anything else.
We can--however--do multiple things at the same time.
And the concept of a job makes it very easy.
A job is just a process that you own, and you started from your console window.
Let's see how to manage jobs on our computer.
Now I have my console open; let's open a file with Nano.
And I am just going to open up Nano to a new file we'll call demo.txt.
So this will create a new file for us to edit.
So I have Nano open; it takes up my entire screen.
But what if I want to run another command?
I can't because Nano is blocking me.
So if I type some words like, "hello, this is some text." and I want
to--maybe--move my cursor back.
And I want to go and run another command--well I could
exit out of the program which probably means I need to write out my file,
and maybe I am not ready to save.
Or even if I am, I could lose my place in the file, and it is really inconvenient
to have to close my text editor to simply run another command.
Now right now I do have the option of opening up another tab and running it there,
but sometimes that's not the ideal solution.
I may only have 1 terminal available to me.
So what can I do? Well--we could simply pause this job.
We refer to a job as a process that really belongs to you.
We saw that processes have IDs, and they are usually 4 or 5 digits long
because they are allocated to the system, and there are a lot of processes.
Jobs--however--belong to you in your session, so they can have
job numbers like 1, 2, and 3 which are easier to work with.
So this process is a job that i'm running, and I can pause it.
In order to do that, I'll hold down the CTRL key and hit Z.
So we can see that Nano has apparently closed.
We see some info here; this may not be displayed to you every time
you do this or on every system, and it's useful to see, but let's take a look at what's going on.
It says use "fg" to return to Nano, which we will see in a moment.
Then we see a list of our jobs.
The number in the square brackets is the job number.
This is not the process ID, but this is the job number we can use to refer to it.
Then it gives us its state, and right now it's stopped.
That's more like paused because it can be resumed easy.
It doesn't mean that we've killed it entirely; its state still exists and we can
resume right where we left off, but it's not running in the forefront,
and it's really not running at all. It's sort of in a suspended state.
And then it gives us the name of the process that is that job.
In this case it was nano demo.txt.
So i am free to run commands as normal--ls, cd documents.
And if I want to go back to Nano, I can use the "fg" or foreground command.
Now it's going to just simply resume the last stopped process we have.
In our case, we only have 1 process in a stopped state.
So it's simply going to take the thing that we most recently paused
and bring it back to the foreground for us to work with.
As you can see, all of our info is here.
We never saved it, but my cursor was in the same place, and it maintained its state.
Now by hitting CTRL + Z I can stop it again.
And you can see it gave us more information on how to get back to it.
We can find out more by using the jobs command.
Here we can see we have 1 job; it's stopped, and it's the one we were working on.
And notice--it now says, "wd" that's because the process started in a different working directory.
So it is giving us some information that the process is running
from a home directory even though we're in a different one.
It may or may not be useful information to you, but that's what's changed now.
So we could do other things--for instance--I could start up top.
Now generally I don't necessarily pause this because it's easy enough to get back into,
but for demonstration I can do the same thing.
Holding down the CTRL key, hitting Z, and now we can see it's stopped top.
And we can see that it has job number 2.
If I run jobs one more time, we can see we now have 2 jobs.
So if I hit "fg" what is going to happen?
You'll see that it foregrounded the last job that I stopped.
And if I go ahead and I stop it or pause it again--
let's take a look at jobs one more time--I still have 2 things.
So what if I want to open up Nano?
Well this is where the job number comes in.
We do "fg" and then the name--number of the job--1.
And now I have opened up number 1 even though top is still suspended as job number 2.
Once again, I am going to hit CTRL + Z to stop it again.
And let's take a look at our jobs one more time.
You'll notice that it's mostly the same--our Nano is still
job number 1, and top is still job number 2.
But now you can see what the plus and minus indicator means.
Plus means it's going to be the one that runs by default.
So if I were to "fg" again, it is going to open up Nano.
I am going to exit out without saving by holding down CTRL and hitting X.
And I am going to answer no, and now I only have one job.
If I take a look at jobs though, we can see we only have 1 job.
And it is still job ID number 2.
It's not going to change as I move around.
So job number 2 is still top, so by hitting "fg" I can bring it up,
and I'll hit Q to exit out of it normally.
Now if we take a look at jobs, it's empty.
Now there's one more technique for managing how jobs are handled.
If I run top and then end it with an ampersand, something interesting is going to happen.
You'll notice that top didn't come up.
However--if I do jobs again we can see that it was automatically put in the background.
Now this is sometimes useful if we have a program running that we want
to not interrupt our current flow, so we can use the ampersand
to send it to the background immediately.
It still has the same properties; we can simply "fg" to foreground it,
and we have it back up.
So if you ever need to immediately background something
ending it with the ampersand can do that for you.