[Deep Dive-Consoles-Processes: Killing Processes with Jim Hoskins] ?[music]?
Sometimes a process can go out of control, and we can't
quit it using our normal means.
We can take one of a few different steps in order to try to
stop the process that isn't responding.
We're going to take a look at the different steps--in order of severity--
that you can use to kill a process.
Now be careful because some of these commands--if executed improperly--
could shut down your machine or cause data corruption.
So we saw how we can pause and resume processes,
but sometimes we need to just kill a process.
Now normally when we exit out of a program the process ends normally.
However, there may be cases where a process is still running,
and you don't have direct access to it.
It's not running from your terminal.
So exiting out of it using the normal means is not an option.
This is particularly true when running servers.
The actual processes that run servers aren't attached to any interactive terminal session.
So if you need to kill it and the normal means aren't working,
you'll need to use the techniques we saw earlier to find its process ID in order to kill it.
Killing processes is done by actually sending things called signals.
There are different signals that specify different behavior.
And these are actually sent to the process which receives that signal and does something.
And these are standardized.
There's a signal called term or terminate.
When a process receives this, it is meant to exit out of the program.
The process handles this by receiving that signal, and then doing
any clean up it wants and then exiting normally.
This is usually the signal we want to send to a process in order to shut it down.
But--there are other signals that we could send.
In fact--we've already been sending signals to the program.
Remember when we hit CTRL + Z to stop a program?
Well that CTRL + Z is actually us sending a signal to our current process
telling it to stop.
Another one we can use is a terminal.
And there's another one--for instance--if I open up
top--CTRL + Z will stop it.
But a different one CTRL + C will send the terminate signal
telling the top process that I want it to clean up and exit.
So holding CTRL and hitting C, you'll notice I'm back.
This has the same effect as hitting Q in this case--however--
CTRL + C is a consistent way to signal to a particular process that
you're running, that you want it to terminate.
You can could see that it's not running by doing jobs, and it's gone.
But what if our process isn't in our terminal?
I am going to open up this new tab.
Just like before, it is another tab into our current computer.
Now if I run top and leave it running and return to my first tab--
if I look at our jobs--we don't have any.
Jobs are per section, which means that we can't foreground it over here
But what if we wanted to kill it?
For instance--maybe if the process that we don't immediately have
a tab available, or the tab is open from another computer,
and we need to stop this top process.
Well let's go through the steps.
So from tab 1, I am going to need to find the process ID.
You could do it by looking at top and hoping that it shows up.
Oftentimes--if you are killing a process--it might be because it's
using too many resources in which case it would be very easy to find using top
simply by seeing what is using the most CPU or the most memory.
But in our case, it is not really going to be easy to find using top,
so instead we use the technique from before, "ps aux" with a pipe "grep" and "top."
Now--again--this returned to us 2 results; 1 of them being the grep command we're running,
which is a false positive--not the top we are looking for.
But the first one is, and this has a process ID of 1450.
So--if I want to kill this process I'll use the kill command.
Now the kill command is something you want to use with care.
Obviously, if you type in the wrong process ID you could kill a process you didn't mean to,
including a system process that is keeping your system running.
So before hitting enter make sure you review things,
and be sure it's really what you want to do.
Now based on permissions in your normal treehouse or normal user role,
you may be stopped from interacting with some processes that you don't own.
But, if you are using a tool like Pseudo to run as a super user
combined with kill, then all bets are off.
You need to make sure that you are running kill on the correct process,
otherwise who knows what could happen.
So 1450 is the target I want to kill.
And we can see that it's still running in tab 2.
So let's type in, "kill 1450." I am going to double check that I typed in the right number.
And just hit enter.
So let's take a look at what happened on tab 2.
You'll notice it's now quit out of it.
The process has been killed, and if we run "ps aux" through grep--
looking for top one more time.
We'll see that the only result we get is the search--
meaning that our process has ended.
Now--by default--kill sends the term or terminate signal to the process.
And this is usually what we want to do.
But sometimes a process can get in a state where it's
not even looking at those signals coming in.
So it can't even see that you're sending a terminate signal to it.
Now this is where we need to escalate things.
I don't have an easy way for me to emulate that,
but I want to show it to you just so you know what it looks like.
So I am going to open up top again from tab 2.
And we are going to use "ps" once more to find the new process ID
since it will have changed. It is now under 1456.
So using the kill command, we can send an option.
What we did before is equivalent to sending dash term.
But the actual names that you send could vary from system to system.
Usually term is dash term, or you could see it written as sig term meaning signal term.
And there's also numbers associated with them.
In our case, it could be 15.
And so by doing this--1456--we are sending a normal terminate signal.
But sometimes that doesn't work.
So if we wanted to send a different signal this is the last resort--dash kill or dash sig kill
is the equivalent, and its number is usually 9.
So sometimes you might see kill dash 9--that means we are going to
send the kill signal.
And this overrides the process.
It's not a request to the process for it to clean up and stop.
It means we are going to turn this process off immediately.
Now there's nothing the process can do to stop it.
This is forcing it to kill the process, which is why it's our last resort.
Now we want to avoid this when we can, and only use it when the term signal is not working
because it may have files open, it could leave things in an unusual  state.
So use it with care
So I am going to send kill to our process just so you can see--1456.
And I am definitely double checking.
And now if we go to tab 2 we'll see something weird.
Our prompt is actually on this line right here.
And the previous text is still in our terminal.
Now it's just there because it hasn't been cleared.
We can continue writing, and anything we do will overwrite it.
But this just shows you what kill does.
When we send a normal terminate signal,
the top command was able to clear out anything that we saw before,
and appropriately place our new command line at the bottom of it.
However, the process just stopped, so our new cursor
kind of appeared wherever it needed to be.
And it didn't get a chance to clean up after itself.
So this is one of those things where you'll see that it leaves your computer in an usual state.
It will still work; we can run clear and it will bring everything back to normal.
But that's how you absolutely kill a process.
Let's just try one more thing--I am going to open up top one more time from tab 2.
Everything is still working.
Let's go ahead and clear, and I am going to us "ps" to find the new process ID of that top instance.
Let's try kill dash stop.
And then 1463.
So it is running right now in tab 2, and in tab 1 if I send stop--let's see what happened.
Again--we can see the same issue where our command line is in
the middle of the output of our previous process.
This usually only happens when there's full screen apps
because of the way it is redrawing all the characters on the screen.
But you'll notice that it says 1 + stopped here, and let's go ahead and clear--
just so we can get all this mess out of here.
If we run jobs now, you'll see that it is exactly as though we hit CTRL + Z.
So I could--from this tab 2 here--"fg"--and we're back up.
So you can see that even from another terminal,
we are able to stop it by simply doing that.
Now if I do "ps aux" again, this didn't actually kill the process--
it just sent the signal to stop it.
So kill is really about sending signals, not necessarily entirely  destroying a process.
And you'll notice it's still is 1463 because it is still the same process and it's back up and running.