[Deep Dive]
[Console Environment & Redirection: Find + Grep, with Jim Hoskins]
Quite often we want to find files, or even find text within certain files on our computer.
Now since it's a console, we don't have a handy search box,
like we do in most modern graphical operating systems.
Instead we programs that run the search for us.
The 2 main tools we utilize are called Find and Grep.
Find allows us to locate a file based on its name, using patterns,
and Grep lets us search within files for a certain pattern as well.
Let's try them out.
So of the 2 main commands we use for searching our system,
we'll be looking at Find first.
Find is used to locate files based on the file name.
It's simply done by typing find, and then we give it a directory to base its search off of.
Now let's say we wanted to base it off of our current directory.
Well the current directory is represented by a dot,
which means we want to start our search from our current directory
and search all the directories below it.
Then we'll give it something to find.
The way we do this is usually by simply typing -name,
and then our next argument is the name of the file.
So if we did "how_to_go_home.txt",
this will find the file called how_to_go_home.txt,
based on our current directory.
Now the results are listed 1 per line,
and it's going to give us the path to the files found.
So in this case it's saying that how_to_go_home.txt is in our Documents folder.
Now right now we don't have very many files in our home directory to search for,
but if you had many, many directories,
and you knew you had a file somewhere called how_to_go_home.txt,
the Find command could be particularly useful.
Oftentimes you'll want to search on the entire system.
Now this can take a long time, because it has to go through your entire system,
but if you wanted to do that, you would start your search at /, or the root.
Let's say I want to find a config file that I know is called "sudoers".
Now notice that I used quotes here; however, I'm not using quotes here.
You don't always needs quotes; however, it's a good idea to put them on.
By using quotes, you can have multiple words used as 1 argument,
as well as use some other special characters.
Now this particular command doesn't require them.
However, I'm going to put them on because it's good practice and a good habit to use.
Now you'll notice we're getting some things here where we're getting Permission denied,
and these are actually error messages.
These aren't results; however, they're errors.
These errors are actually being sent to another channel.
However, they're still being printed out to our screen,
so it appears that they're part of the results.
However, they're actually errors, and we could actually filter these out.
However, we do see that it found the file at /etc/sudoers.
Now the reason we got all these errors
is because, well, there are several directories and files on our system
that our Treehouse user is just not allowed to look at.
So if we're searching the entire system,
every time we hit one of those directories or files that we're not allowed to see,
it's going to give us an error message, but it did eventually find it.
So we'll see a little bit later how we could
remove these error messages from being printed out to our screen
when we take a look at pipes and redirection.
Now we can actually specify multiple directories to start searching from.
So if we do find—and we're in our home directory—
so if we did find and documents, and we wanted to also search in our bin directory
for -name "how_to_go_home.txt",
this would search both of our directories, documents and bin,
and so if you really don't have 1 particular point,
but you think your file might be in multiple places,
you can simply list all the starting points you want for your search.
So that's how you find a file based on its name.
What if you want to search for something inside a file?
Let's go ahead and clear our screen.
Now depending on what commands you've run,
the files in your home directory might be different than mine.
If you encounter the problem where the file I'm using is not in your home directory,
just trying using the commands using the files that do exist in your own directory,
or create the files that I have, using the techniques we learned earlier.
I'm going to take a look at our file hello.txt
by simply typing cat hello.txt.
What if we wanted to find out if there is the word "is"
somewhere in this file, and we wanted to find out exactly where it is?
Well Grep is the program we would use.
Grep is G-R-E-P.
The name is an initialism
which means global regular expression print,
which is a process used in several programs,
which means we want to globally search through a file for a regular expression.
Regular expression is a pattern that defines a particular expression
that we may want to match against.
This means that a regular expression has special characters
that allow us to define very complex patterns that we want to look for,
and the print means we'll print it out.
So Grep is a utility that does all those things.
It basically looks through a file for a pattern,
and every time it finds the pattern, it will print out
the line that that pattern appears on.
The 1st thing we need to pass to it is the pattern.
For instance, I'm looking for the pattern "is".
Again, the quotes aren't necessary in this case.
However, as we go and build more complex regular expressions,
the quotes will certainly help.
Finally, we give it a file or a list of files that we want to search for.
And in this case we'll check out hello.txt.
Now it's going to print out every line where it finds the pattern I-S.
So we can see that it appears
on 6 different lines in hello.txt.
We can look for some other patterns.
In this case, I'm going to leave off the quotes, but it's the same thing.
Let's see how many lines of the text have the word "line" in them.
It appears 2.
The 1st result is from that stretch of the file
where there's 1 word per line,
so the word "line" appears by itself on 1 of the lines
and it also appears at the end of the file
in the sentence "Now here is the last line of the file."
The coloring may or may not appear on your system, based on the system you're on.
It's actually an option passed to Grep,
and the way the system is configured, it is set
to automatically be turned on from the Treehouse console,
which is nice, because it allows you to easily
find the actual pattern within the lines that are printed out.
Now there are some useful options to Grep.
For instance, this wasn't particularly useful.
It showed me that there are several instances of the word "is" in the file.
However, I don't really have a sense of where they are.
So something that would be useful is to print out
the line numbers ahead of each result.
We can do that by typing grep,
passing the -n option,
and then we'll give it the pattern I-S
and then the file that we want to search for.
Now you'll see that the output is changed.
Now it gives us line numbers ahead of each result.
Let's do another search.
We see that "this" appears, so let's say
if I wanted to find grep "this", the word "this",
or the pattern "this", in hello.txt.
Now you'll notice that it gave us the lines that we're looking for.
However, you'll notice that it didn't highlight the 1st "this".
The reason is Grep, by default, has case sensitivity.
If we were not interested in the case sensitivity,
we could remove it by making it case insensitive.
All we needed to do is pass the -i option
and then the pattern and then the file.
And you'll see we have extra lines now.
We have "this", which is lowercase,
we have the lines that we saw before,
and you'll notice that "This" is now highlighted as well as the lowercase "this"
because the capitalized T doesn't matter,
but we also caught another line
where "This" only appears capitalized.
So the -i allowed us to do that.
What if we were only interested in lines
that did not have a particular pattern?
The -v flag allows us to invert it.
So we could do grep -v,
and let's say we want to find only lines that do not contain the letter "e".
That's all we need to do—give it the name of the text,
and these are the lines that do not contain the letter "e".
So those were some useful command-line flags.
I'd recommend for both Find and Grep
to take a look at the manual, which you can find for Grep
by typing in man grep, manual grep.
If you search through this and take a look at some of the options,
you can see that there are some pretty useful options
if what you've seen so far does not quite meet what you're looking for.
So here we can see the -i ignores the case,
the -v inverts the match,
and there are some other options that allow you
to use Grep with a little bit more control.
The same thing can be done for Find if you are ever confused about how Find works
and the options you can pass to it.
You'll remember that we actually used Grep a little while ago
when we were learning about processes.
We did this: ps aux, this pipe symbol, and Grep,
and then we passed in what we were looking for—
for instance, let's say, init, the init process.
This is the same Grep program we just learned about,
and you'll notice it's highlighted the same way.
So Grep is useful not only in looking at files,
but even the output of commands using this pipe symbol.
And we're going to learn about how the pipe symbol works,
which is important because it changes the way
you think about how you run programs.
We'll learn about that next.