[Deep Dive Console Environment & Redirection: Pipes and Redirection with Jim Hoskins]
Most programs we've seen have been called
simply by running the program with options and arguments.
The output of those programs has
usually been printed as text to our console.
It turns out that almost all programs follow a special convention
when it comes to interacting with the outside world.
When we run a program and create a process
there is a standard way of inputting to the program
and a standard way of outputting.
These are actually referred to as standard in and standard out.
Normally the standard out is the console's text
and the output from the program is printed as lines of text on the console
and the default standard input is our keyboard.
However, we can change these around.
We can change the standard out to be a file
so instead of printing to the terminal
all the info is stored in a file.
We can also use a file as standard input
so that instead of a program reading our typed keys
it can just read from a file.
Unix programs nearly always use a plain text format when handling input or output.
This has an awesome consequence.
You can take the output of one process
and make it the input of another process.
This is called piping,
and it's one of the coolest features available in Unix-type operating systems.
It means we can have several small programs that all do one thing
then use pipes to join them together into a multistep process
that does something really powerful.
Let's check it out.
So far most of the tools we've used have taken a file name as a parameter
for it to operate on.
For instance when we've been doing grep
we've given it a pattern and then a file name in which to search for that pattern.
But there's also another way that these tools can operate
using the standard in and standard out.
This means, because the default for the standard in is actually our keyboard input,
if we omit a file name from a tool that can read from standard input
we can actually use our keyboard to input our text that we would want to—
in this case—search for a pattern in.
So let's try "grep" and the pattern will be "hello."
Now if we don't pass a file name,
you'll notice that we have just moved our cursor to a new line,
but we don't have a prompt.
What's going on now is grep is using the standard input
waiting for data to be put into it.
Now since the standard input is our keyboard via the console,
it means that we can actually type in our data.
So you can say "hello world."
And as we hit enter it's going to repeat back any line where it finds that pattern.
Now it's still receiving input.
So if i say "hi" you'll notice as soon as I return the line
I did not get anything back.
That's because the way grep works is it's reading our input
and the unit of work that it's actually doing is 1 line.
So as soon as we hit enter our line "hello world" is fed to the grep process.
It immediately looks at the information it was just fed from standard in
and it saw that the pattern that it was looking for was there.
So it sent the output to standard out,
which is also our terminal, which is why we see it here.
However, when I sent "hi" it did not find the pattern
so it had nothing to send to standard out
so it did not appear in my console.
So if I say "hello again," right now this information from standard in
hasn't been submitted to the grep process
so it doesn't know that I've sent it,
but as soon as I hit a new line,
the computer will send that input over to grep,
and grep will do what it does, which is repeat it back to us if it finds the pattern.
Now when it is capturing standard input from our keyboard
it will continue to do so until it finds a special marker called the end of file.
Now when it's reading a file that's signaled by the operating system
when it reaches the end of the file.
However, when we're in keyboard mode here
there is no actual file to speak of.
So in order to simulate that we've hit the end of the file that we're typing right now
what we can do is hold down the control key and hit the letter D.
That signals that standard input file—
or the standard input stream that we have—is over,
which means the grep process will exit, and we are back to our prompt.
Now we can do this with other commands, too.
For instance "echo" if we don't pass at anything.
Now while that might be useful, there are other things that we can do.
Now while typing into the standard input
may not be the ideal way to use a tool like grep, it can be useful.
But let's look at another technique.
So if we take "grep this," and we say the pattern we're looking for is "this."
If we hit enter now the standard input would be our keyboard,
and it would read line by line everything we pass into the keyboard
through grep processing it.
But we can also use a file as our standard input
replacing our keyboard for this particular process.
The way we can do that is with some redirection.
The symbol for this is in our arguments we use the less than sign.
Think of it as an arrow pointing at the process grep.
What comes after that is the name of the file,
which will serve as the new standard input
as opposed to our keyboard, which is the default standard input.
So let's say our file is "hello.txt."
And we can put a space in front of it if it makes it easier.
So this isn't actually much different than saying "grep this hello.txt"
because grep happens to also take file name arguments.
However, some programs may only accept their input via standard in.
In that case, redirection is the way to route a file to the standard input.
So if I run this, we will see that the results are much the same
as if we had just passed "hello.txt" as a file name.
So we've seen how standard input can be changed,
but we can also change the standard output.
Remember our standard out is—right now—our terminal.
When we've done things like "grep this hello.txt."
It's printed to our terminal and then a new prompt is given to us.
But what if we wanted to print this to an output file?
Now some programs may offer an option—often with the dash O flag
as an output file for whatever that program does.
But if it doesn't or if you choose not to use it
you can instead use your standard output
and redirect it to a file.
So we'll do "grep this" and much like input was the less-than symbol
output redirection is done with the greater-than symbol.
So we can do "hello_grep.txt."
This will be a new file that will be created
and filled with the output of running this command.
Oops, it looks like I forgot to pass in the input
so right now it's using standard input to try to capture content.
So if I were to say "this is my line another line."
This isn't what I intended to do, but I'll show you that it still works
because it's still capturing standard input from my keyboard;
however, you'll notice that it didn't echo back "this is my line"
even though it matched.
That's because the output is no longer our terminal
it's the file "hello_grep.txt."
I'll use control-D to close out our standard input.
Now if we look—by using ls
there is now a file called "hello_grep.txt."
So if we were to output it using cat,
We'll see the only line that was put in there is "this is my line."
Now what happens if I run this as though I intended to the first time?
So we'll say "grep this hello.txt."
And then we're going to use the same output file using redirection.
What happens?
Well it looks like it ran immediately, but let's take a look at "hello_grep.txt."
There we go.
Now it says "This is just some more text to make this file really long"
and "this" the line with this in it.
But you'll notice that it overwrote the original copy of "hello_grep.txt"
"this is my line."
That's because when we do file redirection with 1 greater than sign
we are going to overwrite the contents of that file.
So anything existing would be removed.
There is actually a way for us to append.
So let's try it out.
Let's clear the screen.
So if I were to do "grep" let's search for "this" and "hello.txt"
redirected to "grep_output.txt."
Now if we take a look at grep ouput we will see that we get the 2 lines
where "this" is mentioned in the file.
But if I wanted to append to it now the results of searching
for the pattern line in "hello.txt."
This command with 1 greater than sign would overwrite the file;
however, using 2 would append the contents to the end.
So now if we look at "grep_output.txt" we'll see that it starts off with
2 lines where "this" is mentioned
and then the run for where we searched for line
is also appended to the end.
Let's go ahead and clear this out.
You'll remember this command from when we were searching
all of our files for a file called sudoers using the find method.
If we were to run this, you'll notice we get many, many of these lines
where it says "permission denied."
Now this comes because there is actually 2 output streams from a process.
Standard out is the output stream
that is the result of the process that you're running.
So if you're searching for something, it's the results for that search.
However, there is also extra information.
For instance, when errors occur, how are those communicated?
Well, the system is set up so that there is also something called standard error.
And by default that also prints to our terminal.
But we can redirect it separately from standard out
so if we want to, we can separate the 2—maybe send one to a file
or even tell one to be completely ignored.
So let's clear the screen.
And let's run it again, but in this case I'm going to say
I want to redirect all the standard error to a file called "error log."
In order to do that I am going to use a new redirect.
Instead of simply doing greater than we'll do the number 2,
which means we're going to redirect stream #2, which is standard error,
and a greater than sign.
And where do we want to redirect it?
We'll say "error_log.txt."
So now if I run this, all of those find permission denied errors are gone.
Because standard output is still at our terminal
the standard error has been redirected away from our terminal
and is now going to a file.
And we can see that the file captured all of that error information
by doing "cat error_log.txt."
And these are all of the lines in that file.
Now in the case of this find command
I really don't care about the errors—
I'm expecting them to happen.
I want to search everything that I can.
If I don't have access, that's fine I probably don't care.
So even creating a file for it is probably unecessary.
So let's go ahead and delete that error log file by doing "rm error_log.txt."
And now it's gone.
But if I want to do this and not be worrying about the standard error output,
nor having to deal with an output file
there is a special file we can redirect to that will just get rid of all of that data.
It's called "/dev/null."
And this is a file that anything you put into it will just disappear.
And this is useful largely for the redirection purposes.
So if we route this to a file called "/dev/null" all that data will be just discarded
so we can get it out of our way—perfect.
So we've seen how to redirect to and from files, but we can also redirect
through individual processes using the pipe.
So we just saw how grep can take standard input and search through it
in addition to taking a file name.
So if we combine that with some piece of information that we're interested in,
we can use grep as an amazing tool.
And we've already done that before.
For instance, when we do "ps aux" to search our process statuses,
we see a lot of processes; however, if we want to narrow it down
for instance to anything with "bash" in it
it's going to be pretty difficult.
However, this is exactly what grep does, and it's exactly what we've done before.
So let's clear this out.
If we type in "ps aux" right now we could redirect this to a file
and then use another command to call grep and route that file into grep.
Or we can skip a step entirely and use pipe.
So what pipe does is it takes the standard output
of the process to the left of it and makes it the standard input
to the process on the right.
So if we do "grep bash" we're going to get "ps aux"
it's going to not print the information out to our terminal
because standard out is now this pipe
and that output from "ps aux" will now become the standard input to grep.
And we've seen how the standard input can be used with grep
to find lines in a stream or in a file.
And this is exactly what we get.
Now this can be chained together.
For instance most utilities work with standard input and standard output
using plain text, which means we can chain things together
in very interesting ways and get a lot of work done with 1 line of code.
And this is the Unix philosophy.
It has a lot of small tools that do exactly 1 thing,
but because they can be chained together
they can be used as building blocks to build really powerful commands.
So what if I wanted all of this; however, I wanted it sorted.
Well there is a sort program that takes its standard input
and for each line in the standard input it will output all of those lines sorted.
And there are options you can pass to modify how it works exactly,
but by default it will sort it just by plain string comparison.
So if I do "ps aux" pipe it to grep to filter out only bash things
I could then pipe that output, and instead of printing it to our screen
pipe it to the sort command.
And now the sort standard input will be grep's standard output.
So now sort's input will be grep's output
and sort's output will be the standard output,
which by default now will be our terminal.
So what we'll see in the terminal is the sorted information.
And there we have it.
You'll notice that the way sort works, it seems to have stripped out the coloring
from the grep information, which is fine for our case.
What if we wanted to send it to a file?
Well we could use normal redirection
to just create a file like this.
And so now if we take a look at "sorted_bash_procs.txt"
we'll see that output.
You'll notice it changes just because of the processes that are running.
So by combining pipes and input and output redirection
we can get a lot of work done even if the sources of our data
and the destination of our output is changing.
It's really easy to manipulate these things because most programs in Unix
follow the same philosophy, which means they can fit together easily
even though they are all separate programs.