[Deep Dive]
[Console Users & Permissions: Users with Jim Hoskins]
[Jim Hoskins]: Like most computers, multiple users can be set up
on the machine.
Each user has a login, password,
and a home directory.
On the Treehouse console, we have set you up with a user
called, "treehouse" and logged you in automatically.
The password for the Treehouse account is "mike the frog"
with space in between each word.
As we saw before,
the home directory for the Treehouse user on this machine
is in /home/treehouse.
The reason we have a home directory
is it's a place for each user to put their stuff.
If you're writing code or have files to store,
each user has a place that they can put all of their files.
Outside of the home directories are where files and directories
are for the computer as a whole.
By default, these files that exist outside of our home directory
are not accessible by us.
Well we might be able to read the file,
but we won't be able to update it, delete it,
or create new files
in those directories.
Let's see how to create a new user on our machine.
Before we get started,
we are going to ask that you run this one command
if you're using the Treehouse console.
You may encounter an error in this stage
when attempting to create a new user.
This patch when you apply it
will make sure that error does not happen.
We recommend you run this.
This will make sure your system
is ready for this upcoming stage.
From the console type: curl-L
trhou.se/patch01
then hit Space and the Pipe key, which is shift-backslash,
and it's usually above your Return key.
Then type: bash.
Go ahead and hit Enter.
It's going to ask you for the password
which should be "mike the frog"
if you're using the Treehouse console.
If you get this message, you should be good to go,
and you're ready to continue on with this section.
Right now, we're signed in as the Treehouse user,
and we can see that because our prompt is telling us
we're "treehouse."
We can also use a command to find out which user we are currently signed in as.
The command is: whoami--W-H-O-A-M-I.
When you run that command, it'll print out the name of the user
you are currently signed in as,
which is "treehouse," as we knew.
Now let's add a new user.
The command is: adduser.
The thing is, we need to be running
this in a special mode.
So what we're actually going to type is: sudo adduser.
What is sudo?
We'll be taking a look at that in just a couple of minutes,
but if we type this in with adduser,
it's going to ask us for our password.
That's the password for our currently logged-in user, Treehouse.
As we can see, by default
the password is "mike the frog"
with the spaces between the words.
So I can just type that in,
[typing]
and you'll see when the password is prompted on the command line,
it does not give you feedback as to what you're typing
so you're not typing your password for everyone to see.
If you hit Enter, and it succeeds,
it'll begin the program.
One thing I left off is the name of the user we want to add
so I'm going to try that one more time.
I'm going to hit Up just to do "sudo adduser" again,
and, first, we need to supply the name of the user
we want to add.
For instance, let's add a user for Mike.
If I hit Enter,
you'll notice it didn't ask me for my password again
because I recently typed it in.
Let's take a look at the lines.
It's creating a new user, "mike,"
and it's creating a new group, "mike,"
and associating that user with the group.
We'll learn more about groups when we learn about permissions next.
Then it creates a home directory.
Remember, the home directory is in /home/username
so it created a directory called "/home/mike"
and it copied some files to get that home directory started.
Now it's asking us for a password for the Mike user.
I'm going to type one in.
I'm going to give him the password, "html5."
Then we have to type it again.
We should see that the password
was updated successfully.
Now the adduser command
is going to ask us for some information about the user.
This is not all strictly necessary.
It's really just data about the user
so if you wanted to know the user's full name
or other information about them,
you'd have a way to look it up.
It's not entirely required for us to type it in,
but it's nice to put a little bit of information.
So I'm going to type in "mike the frog"
and you'll see things like "room number"
and these are sort of outdated.
You can think of them as where their office is located
or other information.
If you don't want to type it in, you can just hit Enter to leave it blank.
Phone numbers we don't have,
and if you just want to have some other information
associated with the user,
you can.
Now it's going to give you a chance to review the information.
We can type in "Y" for yes
or "N."
These types of prompts are pretty common,
and you'll notice that gives us 2 different options, Y or N,
that it's expecting.
You'll notice that one of them is capitalized--the Y.
This convention means that Y is the default option
if we don't hit anything.
So I don't even have to press Y,
I can just hit Enter.
We're still logged in as "treehouse."
We can find that out by typing "whoami" again.
But now there's a new user called, "mike."
How do we log in as that user?
Well one way we can do that is to use the "su"
or "switch user" command.
The way we use that is to type in "su"
and then the name of the user we want to switch to.
In this case, "mike."
All we have to do is hit Enter,
and now it's going to ask us for a password.
This is Mike's password.
So, in this case, since I set it up as "html5,"
I'm going to type it in,
and you'll see that it is not typing the password into the screen.
However, I am typing it.
Hit Enter, and you'll notice
that the prompt has changed.
This is because the prompt is something that can be configured
from user to user.
For instance, the Treehouse user has the prompt set up simply
as the username, the current directory, $.
However, when we logged in as Mike,
he doesn't have that same configuration.
So we see a little bit more information.
We have the username, @,
and the name of the computer,
which looks a little bit random but that's just the name of the computer that we set up,
a colon and then the full path to where you are
and then $.
But the idea is the same.
So we can hit Enter just to bring it down,
and if we type in "whoami"
we can see we are now "mike."
We can take a look at where we are with "pwd"
and see that we're currently in home/treehouse.
Remember, the home directory is really a part of the user.
So that's not my home directory,
but since that's the directory I was in
when I used the "su" or "switch user" command,
I remain in the same directory.
I just switched to a different user.
If I wanted to go home, I could use a normal home command,
like "cd" with no arguments,
and you'll see it took me to my own home directory
represented by the ~ in our prompt.
If we type in "pwd"
we can see we're now in /home/mike.
Now how do we switch back to the Treehouse user?
Well we could switch the user by going "su treehouse"
and typing in the password
after hitting Enter,
but if we're going to revert back to the user we previously were,
we can use the "exit" command.
What "exit" did is it took us out of the switch user
that we were running before.
We were running as Treehouse and then we ran "su"
to switch users and then the exit stopped that switch user command
so now we're back to where we were.
If we "pwd" we can see
we're still in /home/treehouse.
The current location we were in when we were using "su"
to switch to Mike has not affected our current location
in the Treehouse account.
Next we'll take a look at how permissions work.