[Deep Dive]
[Console Users & Permission: File Permissions with Jim Hoskins]
[Jim Hoskins]: POSIX provides a pretty robust
and straightforward permissions system.
There are 3 actions you need to know about:
reading, writing, and executing.
Reading is the ability to read the contents of a file
and writing allows you to update or delete a file.
Executing only comes into play with programs.
Since programs are just files, the execution permission
tells the operating system
that "this file can be executed or run"
as well as who's allowed to run it.
So we have read, write, and execute
shortened to "r", "w," and "x."
For each file, permissions can be defined
on 3 different entities.
Each file is assigned a user or "owner."
If you create the new file with the user "treehouse,"
by default that file will belong to you.
This is an actual property of the file.
Now a file also belongs to a "group."
Each user has a primary group.
By default, that group matches your username.
For instance, there's also a group called, "treehouse"
which is distinct from the user, "treehouse."
The difference is I could add a user to the group, "treehouse."
Each user can belong to any number of groups
but only has 1 primary group.
When you create a file,
a group is also assigned to that file as the group owner.
Separate levels of permissions can be set
for the user owner as well as the group owner.
You can set the permissions for other users as well.
This would be used for a user who is not the owner
or a member of the owning group of the file.
These 3 levels
are abbreviated "u," "g," and "o"
for "user," "group," and "other,"
and in that order from left to right--u, g, o.
Each file and directory has 3 types of permissions--
read, write, and execute--
and these 3 permissions can be defined on the user, group, and other.
This means there are 9 permissions on the file--
read, write, and execute for each of the 3 levels.
These are often represented as a string of 9 characters:
"rwx," "rwx," "rwx."
One triplet for each level of ownership.
When we do an ls-l,
we can see these permissions.
The column shows 10 characters.
The first is "d" for directory,
signifying that it's a directory or file.
The next 9 are the permissions.
The first triplet of rwx
is for the owning user permissions.
The second triplet is for the owning group,
and the last three is for other or everyone else.
If the r, w, or x is printed,
that means the permission is true.
If it's represented as a dash,
then it's not.
You can use a command called "chmod" to modify the mode
or permissions of a file or directory.
Let's check it out.
We're signed in in our normal Treehouse directory here,
and if we type in ls-l
to get the full directory listing,
we can see our columns starting at the left
and our current permissions on those files and directories.
For instance, our first directory,
you can see the triplet, rwx, rwx, r-x.
That means the user can rewrite and execute,
the group can rewrite and execute,
and everybody else can read and execute
the document's directory
but they can't write to it.
You'll see all three of these files
or these 2 directories in one file
all belong to the Treehouse user,
specified in this column,
and the Treehouse group.
You'll see that this hello.txt file
doesn't have an execute permission,
because it is a text file,
and execution doesn't make sense for it,
because it's not something we want to run as a program,
and that the user and group owner can read and write to it
while everybody else may simply read it.
So to change these we use chmod
for changing the mode of a file.
You can think of mode as the permissions.
One syntax for this is by typing "chmod,"
and then we're going to describe the change
we want to make to the mode.
This comes in a few different parts.
The first is who we're talking about for this change.
There's the user,
group, or other.
In this case, what I want to do
is I want to change the hello.txt mode
to allow writing by the other group.
So for the who I'm going to type in "o."
Then we're going to say
whether we want to add or remove
the permission we're about to specify.
Since we want to add the write permission, we'll be using a "+."
If we wanted to remove a permission, we would use a "-" instead.
Then we can say which permission we want to modify:
r for read, w for write, or x for execute.
Since we want to add the write permission to other,
we're going to do "o+w"
which means to other we are going to add the write permission,
and then we specify which file or directory
we're talking about--in our case, hello.txt.
So if I run that,
we can now ls-l to see the updated permissions
and see that it's now changed
to include the write permission for others.
If we wanted to, for instance,
add the execute permission for everybody,
we could do this:
chmod.
Now since we want to do it for everybody,
we can omit the o or u or g,
and we can just say we want to--
oops, it looks like I hit Enter.
Sorry, we'll try that again. There we go.
Like I was saying, since we're going to do it for everybody,
we don't have to specify who.
We can simply type in "+x"
to add the execution permission,
and we're doing that to hello.txt.
Now if we run it again, ls-l,
we can see that hello.txt
is now executable by everybody.
Let's say we want it to not be executable by the other group.
Well, we can do chmod.
For other we want to remove
the execute permission.
It looks like I forgot to type the file I was talking about.
All of these parts are necessary.
Now our command should be correct.
We have changed the mode
for other, removed the execute permission
on hello.txt.
Now if we try to run it, we don't get any errors.
Let's take a look now.
We see the execute permission for other
has been removed.
Since I don't really want to leave this with the execution permission on,
since it's simply a text file,
I'll do chmod remove x
from hello.txt.
Let's take a look.
The permissions are often represented
numerically as octal numbers.
Octal is a way of counting,
but using base 8 instead of base 10.
In decimal there are 10 numerals, 0-9.
When we add 1 to 9,
we carry it over to the 10's place
and get the number one-zero or 10.
Meaning we have one 10
and zero 1's.
Now in octal we only use 8 numerals, 0-7.
When you add 1 to 7,
the answer is still 8,
but the number 8 in octal is represented as one-zero.
We carry it over to the next place,
but instead of being the 10's place it's the 8's place.
So when we read one-zero in octal,
it means 8.
Meaning that there's one 8
and zero 1's.
The reason for this is each level of permission
has 3 permissions that could be on or off.
That means there are 8 possible combinations that it could be,
which can be represented through the digits, 0-7.
The permission may be 742
where 7 represents the user,
the middle digit represents the group--4,
and the last digit is for the other users.
So how do we remember which digits 0-7
represent which levels of permission?
It's actually pretty easy.
Each permission is assigned a value.
R is assigned 4, w is assigned 2,
and x is assigned 1.
For each permission that's given or granted,
we sum the corresponding values together.
For instance, if all three are given,
the result is the number 7
because 4+2+1=7.
If we give no permissions,
then it's going to be 0 because nothing would be added together.
If we allow reading and executing,
it would be 5.
If we allowed only reading, it would be 4.
And, of course, if none of the three are given, it would be 0.
Now we'll be able to assign absolute permissions
by using a 3-digit octal number
where the leftmost digit is the user,
the middle is the group, and the last digit is other.
We can use this in chmod to do that.
Let's check it out.
So the octal form is much the same. Let's take a look at our current permissions.
We see what we have there.
Now if we were to convert these columns to a number,
remember r represents the number 4,
w is the number 2,
and the x permission is number 1.
So for this triplet, the first digit would be 4+2, which would be 6.
This one would also be 6,
and this one would also be 6.
What if I wanted to add the execution permission
for everything on hello.txt?
Well what I can do is chmod,
and now I have to think about
exactly what that would mean numerically.
By adding the execute permission,
this would be 4+2+1
since we're adding the execute permission
as the number 1.
So this digit would be 7 for the user.
The second digit
would be 7, and the last digit would also be 7,
and 777 is pretty much opening the file
to be modified or used or completely unprotected.
Generally, you don't want to make a file like that,
but let's just try it out.
So it's chmod, and instead of using the letters
and numbers and symbols,
we'll simply type in the 3-digit code,
777, and again we have to type in the file
that we want to modify.
We hit Enter, and if we take a look again,
and we get ls-l,
we can now see everything is set.
Now I want to make it so I can
read and write as the user.
I want the group to be able to read,
and I want other people to not be able to do anything.
So let's figure out how to modify that.
I want to remove the execution permission
for everybody, because, like we've been saying,
it's a text file; it doesn't really need to have the execute permission.
What we'll do for the user,
the first digit we need to have read and write,
and that adds up to 6,
because 4+2=6.
So our first digit is 6.
For the group, I want them to be able to read,
but not write or execute.
Read is 4,
and since we're not doing the other ones,
that's the number we're going to use.
For other, I don't want them to have any permissions
so I can type in "0,"
and that should be the correct permissions
for me to be able to read and write,
for my group to only be able to read,
and for everybody else
to not be able to read, write, nor execute it.
We need to tell it what we want to change,
and if we hit Enter,
type in ls-l,
and take a look, we can now see
we have the desired permissions.
I can read and write, my group can read,
and other can do nothing.