[Deep Dive-Console: Users & Permissions: File Ownership with Jim Hoskins] ?[music]?
So we've seen how to change the permissions
for users, groups, and others, but we can also change
who is the user owner and the group owner.
Now this is independent of the actual permissions.
When we change the owner, the permissions given for the owner
of the file are still the same, however, it just refers to a new owner.
We can actually use chown which is like chmod, but instead of changing the
mode of it we are going to be changing the owner of it.
Let us take a look--so we type in LS-L, and we can see for hello.txt
you see the owner of the file can read and write, the group owner can
read, and everybody else can do nothing.
And that applies to the Treehouse user and the group as a Treehouse group.
But what if I wanted to change the user that this hello.txt file belongs to?
Well, let us try it out; what we can do is we could type in chown
and the name of the user we want to switch it to.
And since we created that Mike user let us use that.
We do chown Mike, and we will say that hello.txt should now belong to Mike.
Now what we have got here is an error that says we are not allowed to do that.
Now this is something we saw similar before where we had to type in SUDO
in order to run the command because of the permissions associated with running that command.
So we can type with a SUDO in front of it Mike Hello.txt.
Now when changing ownership this may be necessary
because this will override any permissions.
Now--like before--it is going to ask us for our password for our current user
which is still Mike D Frog.
So now if we type in LS-L we will now see the Hello.txt file
belongs to Mike; now it still belongs to the group Treehouse
which means that now me--as the Treehouse user and member of the Treehouse group--
the most I can do with this is read the file.
I cannot write to it. Let us see what that means.
So I could type in cat Hello.txt.
And we can see that the file is able to be printed to our screen
which means I read it. Let us try typing nano Hello.txt.
Now it opened it up fine because all that needs to do is read the file into our text editor.
But you will see we are even getting a warning at the bottom
warning there is no right permission
which means that if I try to change this I may be changing this to high
And I try to save the file by doing control O to write out saying file name to write
Hello.txt which is the current one.
And we now see error writing Hello.txt permission denied
because I no longer am the owner of that file, and I no longer have
enough permissions to write to it.
So I am going to exit by holding down control and hitting X.
It is going to ask me if I want to save; I do not because I am not allowed
to save, and this really is not that important.
If it were, we could just try to say yes and save it under a different name
that would allow us to save a new copy of it that belongs to us,
but it is not really worth it right now.
So I am going to just type in N, so we will discard that change it was trying to make.
Now we saw chown can change the user, but if you want to change the group
it comes after a colon; so if we want to change it to the user Mike
and the group Mike we can do it just like that.
If we type in LS-L we will now see that the user and group are both Mike.
Now if I wanted to edit it, one thing I could do is just su to Mike--
remember this is Mike's password it is prompting us for.
So HTML5 in my case.
Now if I typed in nano Hello.txt I could modify it.
You will see there are no errors being displayed at the bottom.
I could type control X; I will save it by typing Y, and it did it just fine.
If we do cat Hello.txt, and if we scroll up we will see the change that has been reflected.
So I am going to exit out of that--switch user so we get back to the Treehouse command.
And I want to switch it back to being our file, so SUDO chown
Treehouse, Treehouse Hello.txt.
Now if we take a look with LS-L, we will see everything is back how we left it.