[Deep Dive-Console: Users & Permissions: SUDO with Jim Hoskins] ?[music]?
So we have seen how permissions can be used to secure files and folders,
but what happens if you do not have the permissions needed
to do what you need to do.
Well, it may be that you are on a system that does not belong to you,
and you just are not allowed to muck around with those files period.
But often you are the owner of your computer or server, then what can you do?
One option is to log in to a user that does have permissions to operate on that file.
We saw this earlier with the SU or switch user command.
There is a special user on nearly every computer called root.
The root user overrides every permission on every file
and can do anything.
If you know the password for the root user you can use
the SU command to switch to the root user.
Then you can do what you have to do and switch back.
Now this is less than ideal because it requires 3 steps.
Root is all powerful, and this can be convenient, but very dangerous.
Executing a dangerous command as root accidentally is a very real problem.
Instead--it is better to do your day to day work as a normal user,
and then use root privileges only when needed.
This is a better solution all around.
So if you set up a computer or server and you only have the root user
one of the first things you should do is set up a normal user that you can use from day to day.
Locking into the root user is also less than ideal
because it requires you to switch to root, run a command, and switch back.
Also, it requires everybody to have the root password in order to do these tasks.
If an employee has the root password and then needs to be revoked
access from that machine, it requires changing the root password
and communicating it to the remaining authorized users.
Instead--there is a command called sudo or sudo
that allows you to run a command with the privileges of root
without explicitly switching to the root user or needing to know the root password.
Let us take a look at how that command works.
So the sudo command--we have actually run it before.
In fact--the last couple of times we have had to use it in order to
get around some permission problems.
And that is exactly what it is for
in order to execute a command as the super user.
So--for instance--when we try to do chown to Mike--our Hello.txt file--
we did not have the permission to do that because of how the permissions were calculated.
So by running that we had an issue; we are not allowed to
because the operation is not permitted, and that is a pretty common error
which indicates that you will need to run it as the root user or using sudo.
And the syntax of it is pretty easy to remember.
We can just type sudo and then the command we want to use.
Chown Mike Hello.txt.
So we can just add our commands after sudo and a space.
Now sudo is--by default--going to require a password for us to use.
Now this is not the password of the root user we are running it as;
it is our password.
Sudo is a system that grants permissions to other users to use it,
and so it is going to ask for my password because it says I am allowed
to use it as a Treehouse; I am okay to use sudo, but it also
requires me to know my own password.
And this is just to make sure somebody does not--you know--
have your account, and then do something destructive
because a lot of the times the commands you will be running
under sudo can be destructive or can mess up your system.
So it is really good to make sure that it is not going to happen
just by anybody typing it in.
It really should be you--the user--and by providing your password you prove that.
It also gives you a moment to sort of consider the command that you are running--
maybe pause to make sure that is the correct command
because if you write an incorrect command you could mess up some files.
But in this case I know what I want to do, I have had a second to think about it,
I am going to type in the password for the Treehouse user
which is still Mike the Frog for me.
And if we do not get any errors, then it worked.
We can confirm for at least that command by typing LS-L
and seeing that the command happened.
I am going to go ahead and revert it back by doing a
sudo chown Treehouse, and we will hit enter.
And you will notice that the sudo did not prompt me for my password that time.
That is because with the default set up for sudo
it will remember that you have typed in your password
for some specified amount of time.
If you do not use sudo for a while, you run some other commands,
or you step away from your computer and then try to use it again
after that short amount of time you will be prompted once again for your password,
but after you have typed it in it won't annoy you for a little while.
So you can simply use it.
Again--be careful because now you do not have that password to--sort of--
stop and think about the command that you are running.
So if you type in sudo and something dangerous like removing
all the files on your computer it is just going to go ahead and do that.
So--again--sudo requires extreme caution when using it.
Once again, we can just confirm that it worked by typing in LS-L,
seeing that the file now belongs to Treehouse again,
and everything is good.
Now here is a neat little trick.
If I type in a command like, "Who am I?"
to type it to print out my name,
there is a special character shortcut for the last command that we ran.
By typing in exclamation point, exclamation point,
when we run this command these 2 characters will be replaced
by the previous command that we ran.
For instance--it was, "Who am I?"
So by typing exclamation point, exclamation point or sometimes
referred to as a bang, we can hit enter.
You can see it printed out the command that it ran, "Who am I?" as well as
the output from the command.
Now this is cool when it comes to sudo because it provides you
a really easy way to correct a mistake where you should have used sudo.
So if we try that chown again to switch to Mike,
and we want to change Hello.txt, we forgot to sudo.
And we have seen before that it simply will not work.
So I hit enter, and we got an error.
It does not work; it is not permitted.
So--you know--the way around it that we have been doing before
is maybe recalling it, moving our cursor to the beginning,
and typing sudo, but there is another way.
Since our last command was chown Mike Hello.txt
it is represented with the 2 bangs.
Now if we type in sudo exclamation point, exclamation point--
remember that these 2 characters will be replaced by chown Mike Hello.txt.
And if we hit run we can see it prints out the command that was actually run,
and it has the effect of running it which we can see by typing LS-L. once again
seeing it belongs to Mike, and it works.
So that is a handy little trick; it is actually kind of nice and coincidental
because--sort of--the exclamation point means you are screaming at it
because it told us, "No." It is like, "We want to change this file."
And it is like, "No." And we are screaming, "Yes."
And then it does; so it is sort of a fun little thing because it can kind
of make you a little bit angry when you do not have the permissions,
and using a little bit of emotion it is kind of a nice little feeling
to do sudo exclamation point, exclamation point to yell at your computer
to listen to you and do what you want, and it will work.
So just to show you that one more time, if I chown back to Treehouse
Hello.txt--again--we get that error sudo bang bang, and it worked.
Now the sudo command will only work if your user is authorized to use it.
Now we are not going to get into all the configuration for setting up
a new user under sudo, but if your computer configuration
allows your user to use sudo it is a great tool
and will be necessary in future things like installing programs
or configuring system files.