[Deep Dive]
[Setting up a Server - Installing Software - with Jim Hoskins]
Often, we want to install software via the console.
When using Linux, we usually install things a little bit differently
than you may be used to on Windows or OS X.
Instead of graphical step-by-step installers,
we usually do one of two things:
either compile the source code ourselves
or use a package manager.
A package manager is a tool that is usually associated
with your particular flavor of Linux.
And it allows you to install, update, and remove software
with simple commands.
We'll see how to use Ubuntu Linux's package manager, APT, in a little bit.
Sometimes, what you want to install is not available
on the package manager you're using.
In which case, you'll want to download the source code
and make and install it yourself.
Let's see how.
Now, when we want to install software
onto a Linux machine like this, there are a couple of different options.
The best one is to use an automated package manager.
On Ubuntu Linux that's APT, the advanced packaging tool.
We'll see how to use that a little more in the next video.
What we're going to do here is take a look
at the traditional or manual way of building and installing software
on a Linux-base machine.
You often won't need to do this because the packages
will be available for you for an easier installation procedure.
However, sometimes a package may not be available on your system
for the software that you're trying to install.
Or the version of the software that's available in the package manager
might not be the version that you need,
in which case a manual installation process is what you'll need to do.
I'm going to demonstrate by installing a piece of software called SQLite.
This is a lightweight, file-based database
that can be used for producing your apps.
Now there does happen to be a package that we could use,
but for demonstration purposes, I'm going to show you
how to install from source.
Before we begin, we actually do need to install a couple of tools
onto our machine so we'll be able to build
the SQLite program from source.
You'll only need to do this once on your machine to install the tools.
And if you're not using an Ubuntu Linux, these particular commands
that you'll use to install these tools will be different.
But for us, we're going to start by typing sudo because to install
we'll need superuser access privileges.
Then we'll type apt-get. This is part of the package-manager system.
We'll actually be using the package manager,
this is just the easiest way to install the tools
that we'll need to build our programs.
After we type apt-get, we'll type update.
This command will update the package manager's database
on our computer.
That way when we go to install our build tools,
we'll have the latest up-to-date version.
This command is good to run every once in awhile
to make sure that your package database on your machine
is up to date with the latest version of all the packages
available from Ubuntu.
When we hit enter, we'll have to type in our password,
and you'll notice that it's fetching many different URLs.
These are the databases that hold all of the different packages
that are available for our Ubuntu system.
Now that we've run sudo apt-get update,
our package lists are up to date, so now we can install programs.
I'm going to clear the screen.
And now we'll run sudo apt-get, and we'll use install.
And this will install a package by name.
The package that we want to install is build-essential. And we'll hit enter.
You'll notice that it's confirming everything that it's about to install.
We'll hit the y key and hit enter.
And now we'll see it beginning to install the tools that we've requested.
And now the installation process has completed. Let me clear the screen.
And we can confirm if the build tools were installed by typing which make.
Which is a command that will take the name of a program
and tell you exactly where it lives on the system.
Make is a program that's used for building things,
and it's one of the tools we'll use while installing
our program from source.
The build-essential package included make—
so because we see that make is in /usr/bin/make,
we can conclude that the build tools were successfully installed.
So let's get back to installing SQLite.
I'm going to clear our screen one more time.
The 1st thing we need to do is get the source code for SQLite.
Usually you'll find this on the projects page,
maybe under the download section.
We'll usually look for something that says source code or tarball.
But that's what we're looking for, and it provides source code
on this project in both a zip and a tar.gz file.
A tar file, or a tarball, is much like a zip file;
however, it's much more common this tar.gz extension or an archive.
I'm going to go ahead and copy the link address—
this will link to the tar.gz file, and we'll return to our console.
We're going to type in curl -O.
Curl is a program for making requests from the Internet.
The -O will save the file that we're about to paste in here
to a file on our machine.
And in order to paste, I'll right click and type Paste.
If you attempt to use the control v or command v
paste keyboard combination in our web-based consult, it may not work.
However, using right click on the console to paste
or the edit, paste menu in your top bar
should work for the web-based console that you're using.
Now if I hit enter, it's going to download.
And if we take a look at ls, it looks like we've downloaded it
to our home directory.
Now, I like to keep all of my build files in its own folder—
not in the root of my home directory.
So I probably should have created a directory
and downloaded that tar file into it.
However, I can correct that by making that directory by using mkdir,
and I'll call it source, or src.
Now if we look, we have an src directory, and what I'm going to do
is move that tar file into that source directory,
so it's not cluttering up my main home directory.
To do that we do mv, I can type in SQLite,
and now I'll tell it where I want to put it inside the source directory.
Now if I take a look at ls, it's no longer there.
If I cd into source, there's our tar file.
Let me go ahead and clear the screen.
So the 1st thing I need to do is untar the file.
This is much like unzipping a zip file.
The command we'll use is called tar.
Then we need to pass it some flags.
The flags that we need to pass in order to extract it is -xvf.
Now you may see slightly different flags in online tutorials.
This is a combination that will work for us. It means we want to extract.
The v is going to give us some verbose output so we see
everything that happens, and the f is pointing to the tar file
that we want to extract.
In our case, it's the sqlite-autoconf, and I was able to fill it in
by using tab completion.
So if we run this, we'll see that it listed all the files that it created.
And if I clear our screen, ls, we can see there's now a directory
next to our tar file.
So let's go into that—we'll go cd sqlite3.
And now we're inside of that untarred file.
If we take a look, we'll see that there are some files here.
There are a few basic steps for installing a program from source.
The 1st step we need to do is run a program called Configure
that exists inside of the project directory.
Here can see a configure script that exists here.
So in order to run that, we'll do ./configure.
The ./ means that we want to run the configure program
that's in our current directory.
The dot [.] means our current directory /configure.
If we were to just type configure, the system will look for a
configure program somewhere else on our system.
The ./ means we want to run the program that's right here
in our current directory.
The purpose of this script is to look through our system
and prepare some more configuration files that will be used
to actually build the program.
Now it should run pretty quickly and as long as we don't see any errors,
we should be be good to go.
What this program has done is created a special file
called a Makefile.
If we do an ls, we'll see that there's now a Makefile.
And this is a file that specifies how to build the program.
The configure script was what generated the Makefile
that will be compatible with our system.
Let's go ahead and clear.
So now that we've configured our Makefile, we can actually execute it
using the program called make,
which is what we installed with build-essential.
The simplest way to do this is to run make.
And we need to make sure we're in the same directory as our make file,
which should be the project directory itself.
Now this will usually take a little while.
It's actually building the program from all the source files.
So depending on how large the program is and how fast
the computer is, it could take anywhere from seconds to minutes
to even hours.
This shouldn't take very long, but we're going to go ahead
and fast forward through it.
So now our make command has completed.
I'm going to go ahead and clear the screen.
As long as we don't see any errors, everything should be good.
Now we've built the program, but we haven't yet installed it.
It's built the executables and everything that it needs.
However, they're still all existing in this src/sqlite directory.
To use it, we actually want those executables
to be somewhere in our path.
That way we can just run the executable like sqlite3,
which is the executable that we'll be installing.
In order to do this we need to run a different make task
called make install.
Now because it's already built a program,
it won't recompile everything;
however, it will just move everything that it has into somewhere
that will be accessible in our path.
Now because it's going to be moving those executables into our path,
those directories may not be writable using our current user.
So we'll prepend it with sudo to make sure that when it tries to move
those files into their final locations, we'll have the permission to do so.
Now it's gone ahead and installed everything where it needs to be.
If I go ahead and clear, we can confirm that SQLite was installed.
And I'll do that by returning to our home directory by typing cd—
with no arguments.
Now if we type which sqlite3, we'll see that it's been installed to
usr/local/bin/sqllite3.
And since usr/local/bin is part of our path, we should be able
to type sqlite3, and we can see that, at least, it's begun starting up.
However, we haven't given it the proper command.
And we can see that it's been installed.
Now we're not actually going to be using sqlite3—I've just used it
as a demonstration of how to install a program.
If ever you need to build and install something from source,
the process will be largely the same:
Download the source file onto your machine.
Usually you'll need to untar it using the tar command.
Then you'll need to run the configure script that comes with it.
Run the make command.
And then finally, run sudo make install to install it to your system.
Those are the basic steps.
They may change a little bit here or there
allowing you to pass in configuration flags, but usually that's all you need.
Next we'll see a much easier way to install things
using a package manager.